Hello everyone and welcome back to EnglishPod. My name is Marco.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。我是Marco。
I'm Erika.
我是Erika。
And today we have a great intermediate lesson for you.
今天我们为大家准备了一节很棒的中级课程。
That's right. We've got some excellent real English for you all about cleaning the house.
没错。我们带来了一些关于打扫房子的地道英语。
Cleaning the house. That's a real life situation, so we're going to give you real English.
打扫房子。这是一个真实的生活场景，所以我们会教你们真实的英语。
Exactly. So in today's lesson, we're going to look at language about cleaning the house.
正是。所以在今天的课程中，我们将学习关于打扫房子的用语。
We're also going to learn a few phrases that you can use if you want to ask someone for
我们还会学到一些短语，可以用来请求别人帮忙，
help and maybe if you're a little bit lazy like me, a phrase or two to avoid doing work.
也许如果你像我一样有点懒，还能学到一两个逃避干活的短语。
Okay, well let's get started then with our vocabulary preview.
好的，那我们就从词汇预览开始吧。
Vocabulary preview.
词汇预览。
All right, great. We have two great words for you today. Erika, why don't you tell us
好的，太好了。今天我们有两个很棒的词。Erika，你来说第一个吧？
the first one?
第一个词是such a mess。
The first word is such a mess.
一团糟。
Such a mess.
So when something is a mess.
所以当某样东西是一团糟时，
It's dirty.
就是很脏。
Yeah, or things are everywhere.
对，或者东西到处都是。
Disorganized.
杂乱无章。
Yeah, so you have your clothes on the floor and your shoes on...
对，比如你的衣服在地上，鞋子在……
Okay, so that sounds a lot like my desk at work.
好吧，这听起来很像我的办公桌。
Your shoes on your desk. Yeah, I've seen that. I've been wanting to ask you about that.
你的鞋子在桌子上。是啊，我见过。我一直想问你这件事。
Okay, such a mess. Really, really dirty.
好吧，一团糟。真的真的很脏。
Okay, now let's take a look at our second word, chores.
好的，现在我们来看第二个词，chores。
Chores.
家务活。
Chores is a really common word for...
Chores是一个很常见的词，指的是……
Things you have to do around the house.
你在家里必须做的事情。
Like for example, laundry.
比如洗衣服。
Or making the bed.
或者整理床铺。
Or when you have to take out the garbage.
或者倒垃圾。
Those are all examples of chores.
这些都是家务活的例子。
Chores, yeah. I guess everyone can remember when they were kids, they had chores to do.
家务活，是啊。我想每个人都记得小时候有家务活要做。
Yeah, when I was a kid, it was my chore to chop wood.
是啊，我小时候，我的家务活是劈柴。
Chop wood?
劈柴？
Yeah.
对。
That's a great chore. Playing with an axe.
那是个很棒的家务活。玩斧头。
Maybe if you're a boy, but for a girl, it was not so great.
如果你是男孩也许吧，但对女孩来说，可没那么好。
That's why you're so strong and fit.
难怪你那么强壮健康。
Alright, so let's listen to our dialogue for the first time. It's going to be kind of fast.
好了，我们第一次来听这段对话。语速会有点快。
But don't worry if you miss something, because we'll explain all of the important language
但如果你错过了什么也别担心，因为我们会解释所有重要的语言点。
afterwards.
之后。
Honey, the house is such a mess. I need you to help me tidy up a bit. My boss and her
亲爱的，家里太乱了。我需要你帮我稍微收拾一下。我的老板和她
husband are coming over for dinner and the house needs to be spotless.
丈夫们要来吃晚饭，房子必须一尘不染。
I'm in the middle of something right now. I'll be there in a second.
我现在正忙着呢。马上就来。
This can't wait. I need your help now.
这事不能等。我现在就需要你的帮助。
Alright, alright. I'm coming.
好了，好了。我来了。
Okay, here's a list of chores we need to get done. I'll do the dishes and get all the groceries
好的，这是我们需要完成的家务清单。我来洗碗和采购所有日用品。
for tonight. You can sweep and mop the floors. Oh, and the furniture needs to be dusted.
今晚的。你可以扫地和拖地。哦，还有家具需要掸灰。
You know what? I have to pick something up in the mall. So why don't you clean the floors
你知道吗？我得去商场买点东西。不如你拖地，
and I'll go to the supermarket and get all the groceries.
我去超市买所有日用品。
Sure, that's fine. Here's the list of all the things you need to get. Don't forget anything.
好的，没问题。这是你需要买的所有东西的清单。别忘了任何东西。
And can you pick up a bottle of wine on your way home?
还有，你能在回家的路上买一瓶酒吗？
Hey honey, I'm back.
嘿，亲爱的，我回来了。
Wow, the house looks really good.
哇，房子看起来真不错。
Great. Can you set the table?
太好了。你能摆一下桌子吗？
Just a sec. I'm just going to vacuum this rug real fast.
等一下。我马上用吸尘器吸一下这块地毯。
Wait, don't turn it on.
等等，别打开它。
Oh my god, Marco, what happened there?
哦，天哪，马可，那里发生了什么？
An explosion.
爆炸。
We love a good explosion here at English Flash.
我们English Flash喜欢精彩的爆炸。
We're going to give you as many explosions as possible.
我们会尽可能多地给你们带来爆炸。
Okay.
好的。
So let's take a look at our language takeaway.
那么让我们来看看我们的语言要点。
Language takeaway.
语言要点。
So language takeaway is the part of our lesson where we teach you what we think are some
语言要点是我们课程的一部分，我们在这里教你们一些我们认为在对话中非常重要的词汇。
really important words that are found in the dialogue.
没错。今天的对话中有三个非常重要的词汇。让我们从第一个开始。
Exactly. And we have three really important words in our dialogue today. So let's start
with the first one.
没错。今天的对话中有三个非常重要的词汇。让我们从第一个开始。
Tidy up.
收拾一下。
So to tidy up means to...
所以收拾一下的意思是……
Put things in their correct spot.
把东西放回原位。
Right. So put the shoes on the floor.
对。所以把鞋子放在地板上。
Get those shoes off my desk.
把那些鞋子从我的桌子上拿开。
Exactly. So tidy up, organize things a little bit.
没错。所以收拾一下，整理一下东西。
Yeah. Put things away.
是的。把东西收好。
Okay. Let's take a look at our second word now. Spotless.
好的。现在我们来看第二个词。一尘不染。
Spotless.
一尘不染。
So when you want something to be spotless...
所以当你想要某样东西一尘不染时……
You want it to be really clean.
你希望它非常干净。
Really clean, not a spot of dirt on it.
非常干净，上面没有一点污渍。
Like your desk.
就像你的桌子一样。
Exactly. My desk is spotless.
没错。我的桌子一尘不染。
My desk is not spotless.
我的桌子可不是一尘不染。
All right. Great word. Now let's take a look at our last word for language takeaway. Mall.
好的。很棒的一个词。现在我们来看语言学习的最后一个词。购物中心。
Mall.
购物中心。
M-A-L-L, mall.
M-A-L-L，购物中心。
Mall. Yeah. It's a strange sounding word.
购物中心。是的。这个词听起来有点奇怪。
It is a little bit funny sounding, but it basically means a large building with many
是有点好笑，但它基本上是指一个大型建筑，里面有很多
shops inside, many different stores inside.
商店，很多不同的店铺。
Right. Now in British English, you would say shopping center.
对。在英式英语中，你会说购物中心。
Yeah. I think that's a little bit more common, but in American English, we say mall.
是的。我觉得那更常见一些，但在美式英语中，我们说购物中心。
Mall. Great. So now it's time in our show to look at putting it together.
购物中心。很好。现在是节目中的“融会贯通”环节。
Putting it together.
融会贯通。
Okay. So in putting it together, we take a word from the dialogue and we show you how
好的。在“融会贯通”中，我们从对话中选取一个词，并向你展示如何
to use this word in real English. So we give you a couple of examples of how this particular
在真实的英语中使用这个词。我们会给你几个例子，说明这个特定的
word can be used.
词可以如何使用。
Exactly. So the word that we have for today is groceries.
没错。我们今天要讲的词是“杂货”。
Groceries.
杂货。
Erica, why don't you tell us what groceries are all about?
Erica，你来告诉我们什么是杂货吧？
So groceries are all of the food items that you need to buy at the supermarket. So like
杂货就是你在超市需要购买的所有食品。比如
your bread and milk and meat and...
面包、牛奶、肉类和……
Vegetables.
蔬菜。
Exactly. Those are all groceries.
没错。这些都是杂货。
Okay. So let's listen to some examples on how we use this phrase.
好的。让我们听一些例子，看看如何使用这个词。
Example one.
例子一。
There's no milk. Can you go to the grocery store?
没有牛奶了。你能去杂货店吗？
Example two.
例子二。
Here's the grocery list. I need all of these things so that I can cook dinner tonight.
这是购物清单。我需要所有这些，这样我才能做今晚的晚餐。
Don't forget anything.
别忘了任何东西。
Example three.
例子三。
I hate grocery shopping. I can never find what I'm looking for.
我讨厌买杂货。我永远找不到我要的东西。
Okay. Great examples. We heard some really interesting combinations, right?
好的，很好的例子。我们听到了一些非常有趣的组合，对吧？
Yeah. We heard grocery store.
是的，我们听到了“杂货店”。
Which is where you buy your groceries.
就是你去买杂货的地方。
Exactly. Grocery shopping.
没错，买杂货。
Buying all your groceries.
买齐你所有的杂货。
And grocery list.
还有购物清单。
Where you have all the items that you need to buy.
上面列着你需要买的所有东西。
A list of everything you need to buy.
一张你需要买的所有东西的清单。
Exactly.
没错。
You know, grocery store. I think this is quite a common word in Canada.
你知道，杂货店。我觉得这个词在加拿大很常见。
Probably North America.
可能是北美。
Yeah. Do you say grocery store in America?
是啊。在美国你们说grocery store吗？
Well, if it's a small one.
嗯，如果是小商店的话。
Really?
真的吗？
Like a small store.
就像小商店。
In Canada, I say grocery store for even like a supermarket.
在加拿大，即使是超市我也说grocery store。
Really?
真的吗？
Yeah.
是啊。
I would say supermarket for a large one and grocery store for a little corner shop.
大的我会说supermarket，小的街角店说grocery store。
All of these little differences in American Canadian English.
美式英语和加式英语之间所有这些小差异。
Okay. I think it's time for us to listen to our dialogue another time. This time it'll
好的。我想是时候再听一遍我们的对话了。这次会
be a little bit slower.
慢一点。
Honey, the house is such a mess. I need you to help me tidy up a bit. My boss and her
亲爱的，房子太乱了。我需要你帮我收拾一下。我老板和她
husband are coming over for dinner and the house needs to be spotless.
丈夫要来吃晚饭，房子必须一尘不染。
I'm in the middle of something right now. I'll be there in a second.
我现在正忙着呢。我马上就来。
This can't wait. I need your help now.
这事不能等。我现在就需要你的帮助。
All right. All right. I'm coming.
好吧，好吧。我来了。
Okay. Here's a list of chores we need to get done. I'll do the dishes and get all the groceries
好的。这是我们需要完成的家务清单。我来洗碗和买今晚的
for tonight. You can sweep and mop the floors. Oh, and the furniture needs to be dusted.
所有食材。你可以扫地拖地。哦，还有家具需要除尘。
You know what? I have to pick something up at the mall. So why don't you clean the floors
你知道吗？我得去商场买点东西。所以不如你来打扫地板
and I'll go to the supermarket and get all the groceries.
我会去超市把所有的杂货都买回来。
Sure. That's fine. Here's the list of all the things you need to get. Don't forget anything.
好的，没问题。这是你需要买的所有东西的清单。别忘了任何东西。
And can you pick up a bottle of wine on your way home?
你能在回家的路上买一瓶酒吗？
Hey, honey, I'm back. Wow. The house looks really good.
嘿，亲爱的，我回来了。哇，房子看起来真不错。
Great. Can you set the table?
太好了。你能摆好桌子吗？
Just a sec. I'm just gonna vacuum this rug real fast.
等一下，我马上用吸尘器吸一下这块地毯。
Wait, don't turn it on.
等等，别打开它。
Okay. Great stuff. Love hearing that explosion. That vacuum just is a bomb.
好吧，真棒。喜欢听那爆炸声。那吸尘器简直是个炸弹。
Yeah. In this dialogue, there was some really interesting language that you can use if you
是的，在这个对话中，有一些非常有趣的语言，你可以用它们来
don't want to do any chores in the house.
避免做任何家务。
Exactly. So it's time now for Fluency Builder.
没错。现在是时候进入流利度训练环节了。
Fluency Builder.
流利度训练。
You know, Fluency Builder is a part of our show that we use to take a common phrase or
你知道，Fluency Builder 是我们节目中的一个环节，用来选取一个常用短语或
a word that you already know and show you how to express that idea more fluently and
一个你已经知道的单词，并教你如何更流利地表达这个意思。
more naturally.
更自然一些。
Exactly. So let's take a look at our first idea that we want to explain.
没错。那我们来看看第一个要解释的概念。
Let's say you're watching TV like the woman in this dialogue and your husband wants you
假设你像这段对话里的女士一样在看电视，而你丈夫想让你
to help him do the chores and you say, no, I'm busy.
为了帮他做家务，你说，不，我很忙。
Right. Or I'm doing something.
好的。或者我正在做某件事。
Those are two great expressions, but we heard something a little bit different in the dialogue.
这两个表达都很棒，但我们在对话中听到了一些不太一样的内容。
I'm in the middle of something right now.
我现在正忙着呢。
Yeah, that phrase is great. It means she's busy. She's doing something.
是的，这个短语很棒。意思是她很忙，她正在做某事。
Yeah. I'm in the middle of something.
对，我正忙着呢。
Yeah.
嗯。
And so, Marco, you can tell us about our next phrase.
那么，Marco，你可以告诉我们下一个短语。
Okay. Well, now suppose that you want to say, you'll be there soon.
好的。现在假设你想说，你马上就到。
You might say, I'll be there soon or...
你可能会说，我马上就到，或者……
I'm coming.
我来了。
Exactly.
没错。
But in our dialogue, we heard something a little bit different. Let's listen.
但在我们的对话中，我们听到了一些不同的东西。让我们来听一下。
I'll be there in a second.
我马上就到。
So this is a more natural way of saying, I'll be there very soon.
所以这是一种更自然的说法，表示我很快就到。
Yeah. You know what? I think I use this phrase almost every day. I'll be there in a second.
是啊。你知道吗？我觉得我几乎每天都会用这个短语。我马上就到。
Yeah. Yeah. It's really common.
是啊。是啊。这真的很常见。
Yeah. It means I'll be there really fast.
是的。意思是我会很快到达。
Yes.
是的。
Okay. So our final item today in Fluency Builder is a great phrase that helps you say the idea
好的。今天我们流利度构建器的最后一项是一个很棒的短语，可以帮助你表达
of, could you or would you?
“你能……吗？”或“你愿意……吗？”的意思。
Right. Or can you?
对。或者你能吗？
Yeah. So, can you sweep the floor? Could you sweep the floor?
是的。那么，你能扫地吗？你能扫地吗？
But in the dialogue, we heard something that's a little bit different.
但在对话中，我们听到了一些不同的东西。
Why don't you clean the floors and I'll go to the supermarket?
不如你打扫地板，我去超市？
Great. So this is more natural and it's giving a suggestion.
太好了。这更自然，而且是在提建议。
Yeah. It's sort of a polite way of asking someone to clean the floors.
是的。这是一种礼貌地请人打扫地板的方式。
Right. It's a really good and polite way of saying it. Yeah. I would agree on that.
对。这是一种非常好且礼貌的说法。是的，我同意。
This was Fluency Builder. Now we are ready to listen to our dialogue again at its normal
这是流利度训练。现在我们准备以正常速度再听一遍对话。
speed.
速度。
And this time you'll understand a lot better.
这次你会理解得更好。
Honey, the house is such a mess. I need you to help me tidy up a bit. My boss and her
亲爱的，家里太乱了。我需要你帮我收拾一下。我老板和她
husband are coming over for dinner and the house needs to be spotless.
丈夫要来吃晚饭，家里必须一尘不染。
I'm in the middle of something right now. I'll be there in a second.
我现在正忙着呢。我马上就来。
This can't wait. I need your help now.
这事不能等。我现在就需要你帮忙。
All right. All right. I'm coming.
好吧，好吧。我来了。
OK. Here's a list of chores we need to get done. I'll do the dishes and get all the groceries
好的。这是我们需要完成的家务清单。我来洗碗，并买齐今晚的
for tonight. You can sweep and mop the floors. Oh, and the furniture needs to be dusted.
所有食材。你来扫地拖地。哦，还有家具需要除尘。
You know what? I have to pick something up in the mall. So why don't you clean the floors
你知道吗？我得去商场买点东西。不如你来打扫地板，
and I'll go to the supermarket and get all the groceries.
我去超市买所有食材。
Sure. That's fine. Here's the list of all the things you need to get. Don't forget anything.
好的，没问题。这是你需要买的所有东西的清单。别忘了任何东西。
And can you pick up a bottle of wine on your way home? Hey, honey, I'm back. Wow. The house
还有，你能在回家的路上买一瓶酒吗？嘿，亲爱的，我回来了。哇。房子
looks really good. Great. Can you set the table? Just a sec. I'm just going to vacuum
看起来真不错。太好了。你能摆一下桌子吗？稍等一下。我正要快速吸一下
this rug real fast. Wait, don't turn it on. Has this ever happened to you? Has your vacuum
这块地毯。等等，别打开它。你遇到过这种情况吗？你的吸尘器
cleaner exploded in your house? Well, not a big explosion like this one. Not so dramatically.
在家里爆炸过？嗯，不像这次这么大的爆炸。没那么戏剧化。
Not so dramatically. But I've had this happen to me before. Yeah. And dust everywhere. And
没那么戏剧化。但我以前也遇到过这种情况。是啊。而且到处都是灰尘。
it's just it's a mess. You don't want to have. You know, this word vacuum is really a very
那真是一团糟。你不想遇到的。你知道，vacuum这个词真的是一个非常
American word. Yeah. Vacuum. Vacuum the rug. Vacuum the carpet. Yeah. Vacuum cleaner. In
美式英语的词。对。Vacuum。吸地毯。吸地毯。对。吸尘器。在
the UK, what do they say? Hoover. Hoover. Hoover. Hoover the rug. Hoover the rug. Which
英国，他们怎么说？Hoover。Hoover。Hoover。吸地毯。吸地毯。这
is interesting because it's actually a brand. Yeah. So I guess it's kind of like American
很有趣，因为它实际上是一个品牌。对。所以我想这有点像美式
English. You say, pass me a Kleenex. Oh, that's true. That would be like a tissue. Yeah. So
英语。你说，递给我一张Kleenex。哦，没错。那就像纸巾一样。对。所以
I guess they say Hoover the rug or Hoover the house. Yeah. Wow. You know, I really love
我想他们说Hoover the rug或Hoover the house。对。哇。你知道吗，我真的很喜欢
these small differences in meaning that we have between American English and British
美式英语和英式英语之间这些细微的差异。
English. Yeah, it's fun. Okay. Well, another interesting thing about this is that the man
是啊，很有趣。好的。嗯，另一件有趣的事是那个男人
was doing the housework. I know. He's a house husband. Yeah. So he's the one doing all the
在做家务。我知道。他是个家庭主夫。对。所以他负责做所有
chores in the house. Yeah, that's well, that's the new trend now. Now it's more popular for
家务活。是啊，嗯，这是现在的新趋势。现在更流行
men to stay home and take care of the babies and clean the house. Yeah. Like when I was
男人待在家里照顾孩子和打扫房子。对。就像我小时候，
growing up, my dad would take out the garbage and that was it. My mom had to do everything
我爸爸只负责倒垃圾，就这样。我妈妈得做所有
else. But now I think it's becoming a lot more common in especially in North America
其他事情。但现在我认为这变得越来越普遍，尤其是在北美，
for the household chores to be divided between the man and the wife equally. Yeah, I think
家务活由夫妻双方平等分担。对，我认为
it's fair. Me too. Yeah. You'd make a good husband, Marco. That's what they say, but
这很公平。我也是。对。你会是个好丈夫，马可。他们这么说，但
they haven't married me yet. Okay. All right. Well, we're out of time, folks. Be sure to
他们还没嫁给我呢。好的。好吧。我们时间到了，各位。请务必
log on to our community website and you can leave all your comments and maybe other house
登录我们的社区网站，你可以留下所有评论，也许其他家庭
husbands out there can give us their feedback on what they think about this. Yeah. So check
主夫们可以给我们反馈，说说他们的看法。对。所以请
us out at EnglishPod.com and thanks for listening today, everyone. Until next time, this is
访问我们的网站EnglishPod.com，感谢大家今天的收听。下次再见，这里是
Marco and Erika saying, bye. Goodbye.
马可和埃里卡，说再见。再见。